Have you ever caught a whiff of something and been strongly reminded of a person or place?
你是否曾闻到一丝气味，就立刻想起某个人或某个地方？
It seems there is a deep psychological link between smells, our personality and our memory.
气味似乎与我们的性格、记忆之间存在着深刻的心理关联。
Some research even suggests that smells can influence our cognition.
部分研究甚至表明，气味会影响我们的认知能力。
So, why do smells take us back?
那么，为何气味能唤起我们的回忆呢？
Roja Dove, a perfumer, told the BBC that when we are born, the olfactory bulb, which is the area in our brain that processes smell, is empty.
调香师罗亚·多夫接受BBC采访时表示，我们出生时，大脑中处理气味的嗅球区域是一片空白的。
Therefore, our responses to smell are learnt and very personal to the individual.
因此，我们对气味的反应是后天习得的，且极具个人专属性。
This means that when we smell an odour again, the original and unique memory comes flooding back because of the association.
这意味着当我们再次闻到某种气味时，最初那段独特的记忆会因关联效应涌上心头。
Our awareness of smells is primarily unconscious, according to Andreas Keller from the Department of Philosophy at City University of New York.
纽约市立大学哲学系的安德烈亚斯·凯勒认为，我们对气味的感知大部分是无意识的。
This means we are not actively aware of them unless they are extremely strong.
这意味着除非气味极其浓烈，否则我们并不会主动察觉。
But, low-level smells are still picked up because the scent receptors in our brain are so powerful that we unconsciously register them.
但微弱的气味仍会被捕捉，因为大脑中的气味感受器功能强大，会在潜意识中记录这些气味。
In fact, various studies have found the olfactory bulb sends more neurons to more areas of our brain than our hearing or vision.
事实上，多项研究发现，嗅球向大脑更多区域传递的神经元数量，远超听觉和视觉。
Research suggests that the power of smell can also affect how the brain performs, especially when it comes to the aroma of essential oils.
研究表明，气味的影响力还会作用于大脑的运行，尤其是精油的香气。
Mark Moss, from the Department of Psychology at Northumbria University, found that sage and peppermint show general positive effects on cognition while the smell of rosemary can enhance our memory.
诺森比亚大学心理学系的马克·莫斯发现，鼠尾草和薄荷的气味总的来说对认知能力有积极作用，而迷迭香的香气能增强记忆力。
He also investigated lavender which he says "tends to impair memory and slow down reaction time.
他还研究了薰衣草，称其“往往会损害记忆力、减慢反应速度。
But research by others have shown it to be useful in reducing pre-treatment anxiety in dental and medical situations".
但其他研究证实，薰衣草气味有助于缓解牙科和医疗诊疗前的焦虑情绪”。
So, don't take your nose for granted. It really is powerful!
所以，别轻视你的嗅觉，它的力量超乎想象！